Heat.
[Music]
Welcome to Mental Health Monday. We are
so happy to have you all here with us
this evening. Hello, Dr. White. It's
good to see you always.
>> Greetings, Sister Tante. Excited about
today's program.
>> Yes, I am too. we have a special guest,
but we're going to get uh more into that
in just a little bit. We're going to ask
you guys to do what you always do and uh
let us know where you are viewing from
and um let us know where you're viewing
from because we like to see we know that
um Living Mana Church is international
so we have viewership from all around
the world but we like to see
specifically where you guys are viewing
from. So, uh, we here at Mental Health
Monday are always excited to talk about
everything mental health. We cover so
many different things and, um, tonight
is not going to be any different. Um,
we're going to be talking about health,
uh, but there's going to be things about
mental health, the how they are
connected. We're going to be seeing, uh,
the ways that they are connected and
what we're sharing this evening. So,
please put in the chat where you're
viewing from so we can say a special
welcome to you. And I don't know about
you, Dr. White, but are you seeing your
chat?
>> Uh, there's no now. I just saw Jason
Luxton from Milton, Freewater, Oregon.
He beat out Clint.
>> Yeah. Welcome, Jason. We're missing
Clint. I don't know where Clint is at.
Clint is a faithful. He's always here.
For the past three years, Clint has been
uh with us um so many times here on
Mental Health Monday that we just expect
it to be him. But we are h happy for all
of you being here. We had that two week
break. We haven't seen you guys, but we
are excited again to be here uh this
evening. So many things have happened.
>> There's Clint. There's Clint. We see
Amra representing Northern Cal. But
yeah, there's Clint. Welcome, Clint.
>> Welcome, Clint. You weren't the first
tonight, Clint. So that's why we we were
worried. We were worried. What a welcome
Deborah. I don't know where. Yes. Yes.
Deborah, welcome to uh Mental Health
Monday. And I was just saying that
there's been so many things that have
happened since the last time um we were
on the air. I'm thinking we we didn't
did we do a I'm forgetting. We did a
program right after the um horrible um
Yes. assassination. We did do a program.
Okay. But I think the things that have
transpired after that, we have not been
on the air since then. Okay. And there
was a sad um it was sad yesterday. I was
just you know it was just a Sunday a
lazy Sunday and turned on the news and
there was another um shooting in
Michigan. I don't know if you heard
about that.
>> Didn't I didn't get any details. I
didn't get any details.
>> Yeah. There's just in a in a church.
There was a shooting in Michigan at a
church at a Mormon church. So Oh no.
>> Um yeah. So I don't The last I saw I
think one or two um had died but there
were six injured. And it's just sad
because that you
can't feel safe even at a place of
worship. This is and a lot of stress.
People have a lot of anxiety and stress
over these types of things that happen.
>> Well, it's really it's really sad
because you're going to see more and
more armed guards now.
>> Yes.
>> In in in church settings. And before you
know it, it'll be in every setting.
Actually, I saw someone on the news um
he works in that field in law
enforcement and he said they do
recommend many churches hire a security
team. It's just like
>> living in that time
>> just crazy how it's getting, you know,
it was
>> it really is. And so
>> hearing, you know, what, you know,
listening to programs like mental health
Monday to get tips on how to deal with
anxiety and stress
>> that is very beneficial because of the
times that we're living in.
>> Very beneficial. And of course, we're
always encouraging our viewers to uh
reach out to their own mental health
professional in the area that they live.
um just to always have someone that if
you need that resource to talk to when
you're going through things. So, it's
very important
>> to have that. But yes, we uh want to
jump into our program. Thankful for
everyone who is um who has put in the
chat uh hello and where they're viewing
from. You can continue to do that. We
like to see where you are viewing from.
But we would like to welcome
Dr. Columbus Batiste and we are going to
tell you all about his book and the
things that he is doing as well. So we'd
like to welcome him here now to the
program. Hi.
>> Hello. Hello.
>> Welcome. Thank you.
>> Welcome Doc.
>> Yes, for joining us here
>> at Mental Health Monday. It's so good to
see you. Dr. Batist is actually a a
friend of mine and a friend of Dr.
White. So,
>> absolutely.
>> Just we're just here with friends.
>> Indeed. I I feel I feel privileged that
you all have welcomed me into your uh
virtual home finally.
>> Yes, it's good to be here.
>> We are definitely in our virtual home
and we are happy that you are here and
we know that um our viewers this evening
are going to be uh so blessed by the
information that you're going to share.
So, we are excited about that. But, Dr.
White, can you tell us more about uh Dr.
Batis, please?
>> Uh well,
no.
I gotta pull it up.
>> Sorry. I'm not reading the bio.
>> While you're pulling it up, I'll tell
you the little that I know. So, uh, Dr.
Batist and I
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Dr. Batist and I have uh sat on a
number of uh conferences together. Our
churches are we're very near nearby each
other. Uh he is blessed to have a lovely
wife and uh some wonderful kids. And
yeah, I've had the pleasure of actually
engaging and enjoying uh his family in
some social settings. So when I say this
is not a hostile audience, I mean it. Um
and then you're also going to see why
we're so excited to have Dr. Batist on
because he's just a wealth of
information. Um so I so yeah, we can
obviously get into the the formality of
Dr. expertise being a trained
cardiologist with subsp specialty
training in interventional cardiology.
And the thing that's really exciting, as
if that was not enough, um is that he's
also passionate about prevention.
Passionate about prevention.
>> Um so that's what we're really going to
get into, but I'm sure Dr. Sister Tante
has a formal bio. Um
>> you know, and I I actually don't. In the
email that I got, I don't have the
formal bio, but um you did say a lot of
great things and we're gonna let uh
>> No, no, I I can I can load it. I didn't
Okay, so here it is.
>> Okay.
>> Dr. Gumbas Batist is the regional chief
cardiologist for Southern California
Permanente Medical Group and he's
overseeing cardiovascular care delivery
for 4.6 million patients. He previously
chaired the regional cardiac quality
committee advancing initiatives to
improve care across age, gender, and
racial groups. In 2018, he spearheaded
the development of a virtual cardiac
rehabilitation program in partnership
with Samsung Technologies, which he
continues to lead and which has served
tens of thousands of patients through
lifestyle medicine principles. Dedicated
to advancing community health, he
founded Healthy Heart Nation, a
nonprofit addressing social and health
inequities.
He's an international speaker and
advocate for whole food plant-based
nutrition, and he's published his book,
Selfish: A Cardiologist's Guide to
Healing a Broken Heart in 2024.
put a one in the chat if you are excited
to host Dr. Columbus Batiste here today.
>> Yes, we are. We I'm excited. I'm
excited. Um just just to tell you a
little bit more about the book, it is a
holistic guide to healing from stress,
anxiety, and depression through
self-care, mindset shifts, and
plant-based nutrition.
>> Absolutely. So I mean just
>> all those things. Yes.
>> No question.
>> So decorated. So um so Dr. Batist uh
maybe you know we'll we'll let you say
your first words if you'd like or did
you just want us to ask you questions?
Would you just
>> Yeah. What whichever we're have we're
amongst friends this conversation.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> So I have a question. Tell me tell us.
Um so when somebody sees the word
selfish they think okay how is that
that's not good that can't be good for
your mental health for relationships for
your physical health. So tell us what
how you came up with the book selfish
and what does that really mean?
>> No well that actually is a great
question and I don't just say that just
like I say it to every you know like
that's something I say to everyone. So
I've been in practice nearly 20 years
and so taking care of a lot of patients
and part of my discussions I have I've
had with patients. It would lead me down
a pathway of addressing different
aspects of their needs. So I went into
cardiology thinking I was just going to
be straight narrow dealing with the
heart and I realized that everything is
interconnected.
And so I'll never forget watching I'm a
huge sports fan. And so I was watching I
was watching Michael Jordan and he was
giving his acceptance speech into the
Hall of Fame or somewhere thereabouts
and he said you know what you know in
order to be successful you have to be
selfish.
>> Mercy
>> or else you'll never succeed. And I
remember stopping like what is he
talking about?
>> Kobe didn't say that. Michael
>> it was M. It was Michael. You know Kobe
Michael. Anyway Kobe Kobe follows
Michael, right? They're the same.
they're cut from the same uh car rug and
they have the same affliction. And so he
said, "You know what? You have to be
selfish or else you'll never succeed." I
remember stopping and pausing
>> and it was almost like a movie, A
Beautiful Mind with Russell Crowe and
where he was dealing with a lot of
psychiatric issues. I think he had
schizophrenia. And in this movie, it
kind of showed like the numbers he was
this genius would just kind of come into
place. And it was weird. It was almost
as if the letters of selfish took hold
in terms of the pillars of of care which
was spiritual exercise, love, food,
intimacy, sleep and humor. And these
were all the components of things that
over the years that I would talk to
patients about and beyond the aspects of
of really um just the traditional
medications and procedures and I I would
always kind of for years just tell
patients, okay, listen, what's the last
thing you did for yourself?
>> And they would pause. say, "Look at me."
And I say, "I don't want to hear about
for the kids. I don't want to hear about
your spouse. I don't want to hear about
for your job for you."
>> Powerful.
>> We would talk about things like, you
know, tell me the last thing time you
laughed,
>> you know, and they would pause. I said,
tell me the last time you had a good
laugh.
>> And we would have these conversations.
And these were all of the foundational
pieces
>> that I started really researching these
things that I just seem common sense, I
would say. And it just uncovered this
entire world of power, untapped power of
how each of these pillars can really
impact a person's mental health, but not
just that, their physical health and
more specifically their heart health.
>> Powerful. Powerful.
>> Yeah. As you're as you're talking, it's
just making me think of what I share
with a lot of my clients and making sure
that they are doing self-care.
Um especially parents uh mothers who are
just always taking care of their
children. They actually, you know,
actually getting them to take some time
to do some self-care for themselves,
pour into themselves. No, that's
beautiful that you're able to teach your
patients that. Dr. White, do you have
any Did you want to follow up with a
question?
>> Yeah, I mean, I just I just want I'm
just in admiration of how
psychologically minded you are, um Dr.
Batist and
it might have been in an interview where
you talked about
your experience
uh providing care for your father
>> and how
you you kind of reflected on traditional
medical education and its limits and
feeling as if you know I've got to do
more. um and that playing an important
part in your journey. Um can you comment
on that?
>> Yeah, you know, we all have an origin
story, right? There's things that there
we we come to a fork in the road in our
lives for different aspects. It could be
relationships, it could be our careers,
it could be different things that lead
us down a pathway that we didn't think
we were going to go down. So when I went
into medicine, I went into medicine with
a specific goal to become the best
interventional cardiologist I could,
right? And I remember telling
individuals when I entered when I joined
my first practice, I said I said the
answer and solution to ending
cardiovascular care, we need to we need
to build procedures that can stop this
disease and we have them available.
>> And the pathway of seeing my dad succumb
to a chronic illness, a chron a chronic
preventable illness, an illness that
doesn't have to happen
>> was one that was eyeopening. At that
time I was triple board certified. I was
chief of the local department there and
I could do nothing at all to really stop
that progression.
>> And I'll tell you with the mental stress
and the strain at that same time, you
know, and I talk about this in the book
is that I, you know, my dad loved to get
dressed up whether it was for church or
for business meetings. And he had his
shoes shined. He taught me how to shine
my shoes. And so because of the ill
effects of diabetes, he developed a foot
drop. And so which means that his nerves
were impacted by his diabetes and so
they no longer worked. So he couldn't
flex his foot up which means he would be
prone towards tripping. So he had to
have a brace which meant that he did not
have couldn't wear his shoes any longer.
So, as a big-time cardiologist, I found
a place back in the day that made his
favorite Stacy Adams shoes that would
fit
>> into the foot brace. Therefore,
>> uh, so he was like a kid in the candy
store. He was so happy dressed up with
his shiny shoes on and had his suit. But
little did he know, and I know that as a
result of the pressure from wearing
that, it caused a foot ulcer.
>> Wow. that ulcer then progressed and
became infected and he my dad never
walked again. And so and he subsequently
passed away years later as a result of a
multitude of aspects. And so I felt a
tremendous level of guilt with that that
was I the one who drove this. So not
only could I not did I not stop it, but
did I somehow play a role? And so that
was a dark time, you know, in terms of
really trying to deal with that of
self-gilt and doubt and all of those
things. And I, as I began to search and
I I talk about this, it was only because
of the seeds of resiliency that my
parents they they planted in me as a
child that I was able to kind of come
out of that darkness and see um what God
had. And so, you know, it wasn't
surprising to me that as a result, I
began to search a lot of different
aspects of what did I miss? What else
could we have done? What else could I
have done? Did I not pay attention? Do I
need to pay more closer attention to my
patients? Were there things that outside
that can happen because we understand
that health happens about 20% of health
occurs inside the doctor's office and
hospitals. 80% occurs outside or what
the estimates are. And so what could
have been done to encourage my dad
outside of medicine, his nutrition, the
other components for someone who knew
about what to eat well, but keep him on
that straight and narrow. And that began
the process of me researching.
>> That began the process of me going to
Barnes. It started off simple like
everyone else. I went to Barnes & Noles.
I didn't even go to like PubMed and
searches like that. I went to like
simple places. And then I went then as
that progressed I started going into
PubMed. I started going in and I
stumbled on books that were impactful
that then led me back to a path that
perhaps I was trained in unbeknownst to
myself years ago as a child. And so that
really began to build and I've always
had curiosity about how things work. And
so I started learning about the
mechanism of action of how food of how
our mindset of how how spirituality of
how our forgiveness about how the
intimacy of relationships of precisely
what happens in the body that can
transform your health both mental and
physical health. So I mean that's a
long-winded answer to kind of say that
full circle.
>> That was beautiful.
>> That's beautiful. You know, you know the
question that's jumping off the the page
right now. Uh Dr. Batist, what's the
last selfish thing you did for yourself?
>> Oh, I'll tell you the last selfish day I
thing I did for myself was yesterday was
my birthday. And I I went and I spent 45
minutes in infrared sauna, which I can
talk to you about all the health
benefits of that.
>> That's
>> Then I had a 90minute massage
>> and
>> that's selfish. That's
>> Yes. And then I completely just took
time moments of gratitude in terms of
being grateful for the past year, all
the blessings, um all the challenges,
all the successes uh to reflect on those
things and to call those out um as well.
And so I did those things in terms of
the components of selfish which are
important. I exercised too as well, you
know, I I laughed a little bit. So all
the things I talk about in the book
actually I was able to participate in um
during yesterday's period of time.
>> Happy birthday doc.
>> Yes.
>> Happy birthday. That's wonderful. I love
the things that um you did. The infrared
sauna is amazing.
>> Yes,
>> it's amazing. Amazing. We do have a
question. One of the viewers has a
question. Uh Clint Ies is asking, "Is
there such a thing as healthy obsessive
drive towards goals?"
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. Listen, I I set
a theme for every year, right? And so
that's typically what I'll do when I
when I reflect on on the upcoming year
and what my goals are. And so I've had
intentional as one of my my words of the
year for the past couple of years. But
this time I decided I was going to make
it three-pronged and keep intentional. I
said strategic,
intentional, and unapologetic.
That's where the obsessive component
comes in because what may seem as an
obsession to others surrounding you that
brings is your drive. That's your
meaning. That's your purpose. So when we
talk about meaning and purpose, that's
such a powerful component and it's tied
to longevity and that's a component of
you know people when they find their
their purpose. Now obviously connecting
to um to
God and having a drive and a purpose
that's what spirituality is. But that
meaning and purpose, that connectivity
is such a powerful thing. Now, to
someone on the outside, the fact that
you're driven to your meaning and
purpose may seem as if you have an
obsession. And that's where being
unapologetic as you're on this journey
to achieve your best self becomes
important. Because guess what ends up
happening? That when others want to
have cake and ice cream, they want to go
for a pizza party and you're like, you
know what? I'm going to be intentional
in my efforts. I'm gonna be selfish.
That really doesn't I'm gonna be
unapologetically selfish because my
goals are X, Y, and Z for towards my
health. I don't care that others around
me may not want may look at me like why
aren't you having this? Why aren't you
doing it? That guess what? I need my
rest. That I guess I'm going have to be
selfish in that moment and I'm going to
get my rest. that you know there takes a
level of dedication um that that you you
see that this interplay plays a role. So
I do believe that there is a healthy
obsession towards your goals.
>> Well said. Well said.
When do you suppose selfish would be a
bad thing?
Well, I think I think anytime that you
know I and so now I'm a I'm a as I
always like to joke with my admin my
assist not assistants but my partners uh
in leadership I said you know I'm I'mma
get outside my lane a little bit here.
So when I get outside my lane a little
bit into to Dr. White's realm and
Tante's realm. You know, whenever
someone is, we all have a little
component of everything, I believe.
Right. We have a there's a little bit I
have a little bit of obsessive
component. Did I lock that door? Let me
go back and check that door real quick.
Um, you know, a little type A, a little
bit of all these little small commot. I
describe being depressed a little bit uh
for a period of time. It's when it takes
over your life, when it's persistent.
Yes.
>> Right. That's when it becomes
problematic is when it becomes
persistent and now despite other things
now it turns into being a level of harm
either to yourself or to others. And I
think there is a there is a fine line
with all those things in terms of
because one of the components of selfish
of true selfish is the eye for intimacy
and intimacy is not necessarily in a
physical form although it does include
that. It's really the it's really the
relationships, the positive
relationships. And when you're engaging
in positive relationships that can be
supportive, they can be rewarding. They
can be uplifting. They can be nurturing.
Sometimes you have to give a little bit
to maintain those pos those
relationships, right? You have to give a
little bit in that sort of compromise
sort of state. And if you're completely
self-absorbed, you can't give a little
bit for the relationships.
>> Well said. Well said. I I forgot where
and I'm going to butcher the quote, but
it was like maybe I made it up. Who
knows?
It was like it was like if you want
if so actually it was pastor Randy
Roberts and he was talking about how um
what you focus on like if like like we
are on a journey to meet an old man in
the case of Aante it's an old woman. And
when we encounter that person,
what will they be like? And will they be
happy?
>> And if we focus on ourselves,
that man or woman is not going to be a
happy person and they're going to be a
pretty small person.
>> And if we made others our focus,
then that person would be a large and
happy person, so to speak. I mean and so
and I'm just balancing it with what
you're saying. So
>> absolutely.
>> So so I I wholeheartedly agree with you
that we have that balancing it is where
we're going to get that richness.
>> Yes.
>> And and my question basically kind of
summarized Deborah's question which was
what methods should we apply so you do
not lose yourself in self-centerness
while still taking care of yourself. So
I feel like you answered that. Is that
>> Yeah, absolutely. But I mean I think I
think when we I think the first letter
first pillar of spiritual I mean you
know you know if we term biblically and
we say seek ye first the kingdom of God
and all these things will be added to
you
>> that our mindset it that determines our
direction that determines our focus. So
if our focus starts there everything
else follows in line right and that's
going to help guide us as we set our
purpose that will evolve. It's going to
shift. is going to change and it becomes
like a domino right so if if I think of
it in those terms and I start off with
spirituality in in that context and I
move to exercise and everyone thinks
exercise only as okay I'm going to get
in there and do my pelaton I'm doing my
my chin-ups whatever it is my tybo if
you go back to the 80s but if we
exercise belief faith
>> mercy
>> all right so so I mean the studies are
powerful when you look at the power of
exercising belief in that faith and what
begins to transform And wonderful work
has been done out of Stanford. Dr.
Aliyah Crrum has done phenomenal work
kind of looking at the impact even when
you tell individuals that guess what
housekeepers inside a hotel that what
you're doing is exercise that will cause
you to lose weight. Changing nothing
else. Number of steps didn't change. All
of a sudden they lost more weight than
the people who didn't believe it. They
told people, "Okay, listen. You're
drinking this smoothie but this one is
high rich in fat." All of a sudden what
begins to happen in terms of the body
composition based on the mind. Mercy
>> you know and when we compare our
medications
>> and we all you understand this if you
prescribe or you take anything we
prescri we compare it to placebo which
means an inorganic substance has is
inert has no biological activity which
means we're comparing it to your mind
>> and you have to beat out the mind for it
to get approved. But the one thing we're
losing in that is I have to also believe
in that medication
that has some biological activity. So
that belief component plays a role. So
now you move from spirituality saying
your purpose and that's there you're
exercising faith and belief. Now you
move to the expression of love
>> because love is no longer it's not just
a noun it's a verb. And so as you move
to that in forgiveness in gratitude in
volunteering or altruistic efforts now
things the connectivity starts to come
take shape and it takes hold and you're
moving through that. Then you move to
hopefully you're having communal uh food
eatings and we're going to skip over
food and come back to that later time.
Then you're going to the eye of intimacy
of relationships. You're building
relationships because now guess what?
You have your purpose. You have your
belief. You're excit you're expressing
that belief through your actions and now
these relationships are being formed and
you're able to rest and then get joy and
humor in life. So,
>> right,
>> it's all interconnected.
>> It's beautiful.
>> You know, we have another question. Um,
this is from Luetta. Um, I hope I said
your name correctly, but she's asking,
uh, what do we do with esteem others
above yourself, which is, um, a biblical
principle when you're talking about
being selfish? I'd like to take a stab
at it and then I want you Dr. Batis to
as well. Um, you know, even though yes,
the book is called selfish, but
self-care actually is everything except
being truly selfish. You're actually
pouring into yourself. I, you know, it's
like for me to show up to be a good
wife, to be a good mom, even to be a
good therapist, I need to uh do my
self-care, pour into myself so I can
show up and be the best version of
myself. So, you're actually not being
selfish. You're making yourself the
better version of yourself, doing the
things that you need to do. So you have
you're in a healthy mind space so you
can be a good mom, be a good uh mother,
be a good whatever uh your work field
is. But Dr. Patise, please answer her
question from your head.
>> No, you're you're you're absolutely
right and and I mean it's you you want
to engage in the principles of being
selfish as I outlined them,
>> not in the personal not in a humanistic
perspective. A humanistic approach
towards being selfish is it's my my my
mind my mind my mind my mind my mind my
as if you're a petulant child the
biblical Christlike perspective as it
pertains to being selfish is just what I
outlined
>> it's the spirituality it's the ex it's
the the exercising belief it's the love
as an action it's the food whether or
not it's it's uh you know the intimacy
of relationships it's the sleep or the
day of rest and coming away it's the joy
of life those are all the components the
humor that plays a role in truly being a
spiritual a Christlike I believe a a
god- centered selfishness is what is
what you have to to to look at. I mean,
you think of from a biblical perspective
when Christ went away from his kids as a
his parents as a teen and he said,
"Listen, I got to be about my father's
business." Yeah.
>> Right.
>> That's right.
>> Some like, "What are you talking about?
How you going to talk to your parents
like that? That's selfish."
>> When he said Christ had kids, when he
said Christ had kids, I almost fell out
of my chair.
>> No, no, no, no, no, no. When he was with
his parents like that. Yeah. When he
when he was a kid, a child.
>> Yeah.
>> No. Yes. No. Um, well, yes, please put
your continue to put your questions in
the chat because you guys are part of
this program and we want you to get
everything out of it while we have Dr.
Batist here. But I have a question. Um,
so tell us on how being selfish like
with your diet like how what the things
that you um eat and and how does that
affect um your heart?
>> Yeah. So
>> your cardiologist
>> well when I look at I mean we've taken
we've broken food down into into
macronutrients and food has transformed
over the years and food is relationship
food is personal with people right it
brings joy it brings happiness it brings
memories emotions are tied to it that's
there that we know on a regular basis
but when we look at where are the
medicinal properties of food right it's
where the medicinal properties of food
it's clear it's clearly evident the
foods that will transform the your life
really are found in the foods that have
been given to us on the earth right so
fruits vegetables whole grains beans
blooms nuts and seeds there is zero
doubt about it so when I break that down
and we start going through from a
standpoint sim uh from a from your
health whether it's mental health or
physical health and we walk through
those principles and we look at what is
the power of vegetables well we'll take
power of like green leafy vegetables for
instance right pap was right when he
talked about the muscles growing and
eating and the spinach. But we know that
releases something called dietary
nitrates that your body will your as you
chew you begin to transform and all of a
sudden what begins to happen is your
vessels will dilate because it interacts
with the lining of the vessel called the
endothelium that leads to what we call
basodilitation. That's powerful. We also
understand that this fiber that's
contained inside of not just the
vegetables but inside the whole the
whole grains. This fiber what it does it
acts like a sponge. It soaks up
something called bile acids. Bile acids
are like detergents that your body uses
to break down the fats that you eat. And
so when it absorbs the bile acids and
secretes it, the bile acids are made of
cholesterol. So your body has to pull up
pull in more cholesterol out the system
which lowers your total cholesterol.
>> Yes.
>> Decreases the likelihood of plaque
formation or heart attacks happen. But
it doesn't just stop there. Now, these
foods, what they begin to do is that
they feed in they feed what's called
your gut microbiome, right? So, what
many people don't understand, and if you
told me this when I was a kid, I would
have completely lost it. I would have
had to go see Dr. White, that I'm you're
actually more bacterial DNA than you are
human DNA.
>> You're more bacterial DNA and viral DNA
than you are human DNA. And what that
means, you have this whole network
that's living and breathing inside of
you. And everything we do either feeds
the good guys or feeds the bad guys.
That's what I used to tell my kids when
they were small. And so what studies
have shown is that as we feed the good
guys with with fiber richch foods, all
of a sudden they break this down to
something called short- chain fatty
acids. We know that it's going to
release serotonin. We know that it's
going to decrease the inflammation. We
know that it's going to empower your
body to decrease cancer. There's so much
power that's there that is is laden at
your fingertips from it. But it doesn't
stop there. My favorite fruit of all,
it's become this way since I've been an
adult and started studying this stuff
are berries. And berries are so
important. And so here's the reason why.
When you think I mentioned Michael
Jordan, but let's think of any
celebrity. What do most celebrities have
with them? Who's around them down the
street?
>> Trainers.
>> Oh, bodyguards.
>> Bodyguards. They got their bodyguards
with them. They're not going out there.
What's the other thing we know about
celebrities? You kind of know them by
one name.
>> You don't have to be like, "Well,
Columbus who batis, you know, Batiste,
you're not trying." You know them by
name. You know them by one name, right?
Kobe, you say Kobe, right? MJ, you go
one name they know him by.
>> Well, the celebrities of the food, you
know them by one name, one ingredient.
Blueberries, strawberries, raspberries,
beans, greens, rice, singular names. And
they carry with them bodyguards called
antioxidants. What we have to understand
is that our body is constantly under
attack by something called free
radicals. And these free radicals are
looking to take and destroy us. And
these free radicals bombard our cells
and they disrupt the cells. They steal
the joy. They call it electrons. They
steal and snatch it causing that cell to
die. And so when you get these free
radicals, they stand in the way. They
stand they they absorb the attacks from
the free radicals. Doesn't sound
familiar, right? And so as your bo as
you eat more and more of these
antioxidants, you now are defending
yourself. You're loading yourself with
free rad with with bodyguards on a daily
basis. And that's power of eating
selfishly through a plant-rich diet.
Right? So I try and focus on what are
you eating for your health. So when
people ask me, well, what you're trying
to say that this is bad for me. I'm not
trying to say is it bad for you. I'm
trying to say, can you tell me how it's
good for you? Oh, I like that.
>> It tastes good.
>> I like that. I like that.
>> But you have to tell me how it's good
for you. I'm about trying to intervene.
So,
>> uh, Dr. White said something earlier. He
said that I was about I'm about the
power of prevention. And I have to
humbly disagree. I I don't believe there
is any prevention. There's only
intervention.
>> There is only intervention because I'll
tell you what, disease starts from the
moment we pop out the womb. There are
actually studies that have shown that in
some individuals, mothers are smokers.
you get start to get thickening of the
lining of the vessels of the of the
heart in uterero that we know that
atherosceros scerosis begins before the
age of 10 as early as two years of age
it progresses that individuals will have
this and that it's a silent progression
and this goes to multiple disease states
>> that we're all living with microscopic
uh uh cellular death that's leading to
cancer and so we're constantly in this
struggle between illness and wellness
and the question is who are we feeding
the good guys or the bad guys?
>> You know, you just dropped so much
science on us.
>> I know. But I think I think all the men
will want you to expand on your
discussion about spinach and nitrates.
Uh Dr. Batiz, why is nitrates something
that we as as as men will be very
interested in and women too, but
especially men? Well, you know, I'll
tell you there are many bodily functions
that rely upon it, right? So, when we
talk about when we talk about the
ability to procreate to to to one of the
things that men suffer with as they
enter into Well, first, let me take a
step back. One of the things that I
first noticed during watching sports is
that there's always these commercials
about erectile dysfunction medications.
>> They're pervasive. And what's so
interesting is that over the years, the
individuals in the commercial, if you've
ever noticed, and not because I'm
getting older, but the people are
getting younger and younger. Before they
would show like senior citizens in these
erectile dysfunction commercials. Now
they're showing 30 year olds in erectile
dysfunction commercials. They're they're
advertising on social media. And the
question is why? Now, we understand
there's a mental health component that
can play a role in it. We know there's
multiple aspects but I'll tell you the
root cause is a vascular issue. Uh it's
a vascular issue and as the vessels
become restrictive there becomes an
issue that that happens. That's where
study after study tells us the power
that as you begin to eat fruits and
vegetables and whole grains there's
improvement in erectile function there's
an improvement as a whole. But you know
you mentioned men but this also pertains
to women.
>> Yeah. So when we look at women, women
have a superpower literally. So I am of
the belief that women that means that's
a tante is way smarter than what we are.
They have like this level of
intelligence that's that's pervasive. I
believe it. I've seen it throughout
school and everything.
>> You lose your superpower when you start
going through menopause that estrogen is
a superpower. Now all of a sudden as
that estrogen begins to drop all of a
sudden you start becoming subject to all
of the ills that men do. The visceral
fat we start seeing the cholesterol
being shifting the endothelium becomes
impacted because of low estrogen. So we
know the power of the principles of
selfish that really can help restore and
as an avenue to help uh uh uh women as
they enter this permenopausal and
menopausal state to regain their power
and their vitality as much as possible.
And we see the benefits of it and that's
been demonstrated lower rates of hot
flashes, lower rates of occurrence of
diabetes and of of uh heart attacks when
you engage in eating a whole food
plant-based diet. when you engage in the
components of selfish that I've kind of
mentioned already.
>> Well, there's many men in the chat who
are thanking you for sharing that uh
information. So, they appreciate it.
Okay. We appreciate it, too.
>> But you something else you said when you
were uh just dropping all those
scientific facts. You were um talking
about healthy microbiome. Um, and that's
where I know that 95% of serotonin is
produced in the gut. So, you need to
have a healthy the healthy bacteria.
>> Um, so you're saying a plant-based diet
does that that helps you with that?
>> Absolutely. It's a it's a Let me let me
rephrase, but you go first. Well, I just
wanted to say just so um our viewers, I
wanted to just say when we're talking
about serotonin, this is um one of the
the chemicals that help us to have like
the happy hormone that makes us feel
good. And so that's why it's so
important for our mental health. But go
ahead, doctor.
>> Well, I was just going to say, you know,
a lot of things are labeled plant-based.
I mean, if you really get at it, you're
looking at foods that that make you
chew. That means they're rich in fiber.
And it's that fiber that does the magic.
Your soluble and insoluble fiber. So, as
you're having if you and what I mean by
chew is think about I remember back in
the day uh my dad would buy a bread
called home pride bread. I don't know if
they make it or not anymore. And this
bread you it melts in your mouth, not in
your hands. It just you put in there.
You don't even have to chew. It starts
melting right away. And you juxtapose
that with something called Ezekiel 949
bread. You're chewing for days when
you're eating that bread. Yep. You're
chewing for days. And why is that?
Because it's rich in fiber. It's rich in
fiber. And that fiber is the stuff that
makes a diverse microbiome. But here's
hear me with this part. What studies
have shown is that when you have a
diverse microbiome,
>> that your immunity is greater. Your
strength is greater. Your ability to
withstand disease is greater. We're
greater collectively the more diverse we
are. Now, you take that where you want
on a national level or anywhere else.
We're stronger the more diverse we are
across the board.
Powerful.
>> Wow. That is so powerful. I think we
have another another question. Um, does
that also pertain to men going through
um is that
>> andropause at a younger age now.
>> At a younger age now. Thank you.
>> You know, there's so many one of the
things that you're looking at. You're
looking at that's a great question. So
what we're facing right now is we're
facing like a world in which we're
having lots of what are called endocrine
disruptors that are there and that may
be from microplastics. It may be from
the processing of foods. It could be the
way in which we're cooking the foods.
And so we're really under significant
attacks as it relates to the way in
which our modernized society lives. And
that's myself included. And so one of
the things that becomes important,
listen, I want to tell you how
significant it is. I wanted to have a
plant. So, I got this little shabby
little Charlie Brown plant back here
because I don't have a green thumb. And
so, I did not want to have a plastic
plant behind me because of the
microlastics that circulate. So, I
bought one that forces me to try and
water it and bring it put in some
sunlight and everything of that sort. As
you're exposed by water bottles, you're
exposed by packaging and we're exposed
by by processed foods, chemicals we
can't pronounce, nothing we could ever
make. These things all play a role. And
so the everything and this is not to
sound
off the deep end. All right, you have to
live and breathe in and in this world,
but the if I'm able to. So what do I do?
I I just made simple substitutions in my
home. I got rid of the plastic
containers that I had. I got rid of some
of the plastic cups and I bought glass.
No big deal. Whatever else. But guess
what? If I'm out and I'm thirsty and
there's nothing else to drink and
someone offers me a a water bottle, I'm
not saying no way I'm going to die of
thirst and sit here. I drink the water
bottle in that moment, but 90% of the
time I am not. I'm choosing not to do
that. I'm making efforts that are
conscientious. I'm looking at the
ingredients. I'm making every stride to
reduce that effect from a hormonal
standpoint. And I'm that's full circle
back to the question as in part why are
we seeing all of these shifts in our
young adults? Um, and this this impact
of stress, this impact of of our foods,
it's been well documented with females
going through early menarchy and so
forth and and so forth. And we see the
same thing affecting our men. We see the
same thing for infertility for men is
with the uh microplastics.
>> Bro, what's the plant you would
recommend for someone like myself? I've
got a friend. But yeah, like uh that you
would recommend for, you know, sitting
in an office like this. What's the plant
you'd recommend?
>> Well, first of all, are you asking the
wrong somebody? Because I dropped out of
I did not want to do plants and I did
not want to deal with like rodents
inside of biology. So, I took
biochemistry
>> so I could you and me both. That's why
I'm asking you.
>> Yeah. So, I
>> put it in the chat if you guys know if
you guys know that I should get.
>> Yeah. Let it let us know, man. Cuz I
definitely want to step my game up.
>> I bought my grandfather had a green
thumb, but it didn't pass to me. Like, I
buy plants,
>> but they die.
>> And I have a very I have a very black
thumb. Okay, so
black,
>> I'm telling you. So, I I I got this
plan. I was like, "Oh, man. This looks
good. It's going to look all full and
everything." All of a sudden, the leaves
are dying and I'm going back and forth,
but I'm committed to being I'm not
giving up. I promise I want to make this
plant flourish.
>> Yo, props to Noel Gully. Noel Gully. Um,
>> they say snake plants are so good with
with cleaning the air. So, that's that's
your answer to your question.
>> You gota you got to send her a t-shirt.
Sister Tante,
>> say that again.
>> You got to send her a t-shirt.
>> I gota send her a t-shirt. Yes.
>> Email her at info living mana. What is
it?
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. I also we want to uh
we're not done asking Dr. Batist
questions but we just want to let you
know where you can get the book selfish.
So we're going to put that I think and
we're going to put that on the chat and
put um the link so that you will be able
to get that. You can get it off of
Amazon and you'll be able to go through
uh the book on your time and take out
all the amazing um information. It's in
the chat now. So please check that out.
All the information that Dr. expertise
um has in that book. Please um you have
about uh 7 to 10 minutes to ask your
question. So please put uh in the chat
if you have a question for Dr. Batis.
But this has been um already such an
amazing um insightful discussion. So,
for those who are just wondering,
well, you've I mean, you've been very
clear with the science and that a plan.
>> Wait, could we have him could we have
him talk about his conference?
>> We're going to do that. We're definitely
going to do that.
>> I just want to, you know, ask for people
who are wondering, who are just joining
us for the first time and never have
heard of, you know, well, they've heard
of a plant-based diet, but that it's so
that it can be that impactful in their
lives. um you know
how like how what would you say where
should they start if they're just
hearing this for the first time about a
plant-based diet?
>> Yeah. So is that start learning more or
start to experiment and try it out?
>> Both.
>> Yeah. So one of the things that I would
say is that I would choose if I'm just
starting out. First of all, it's not as
foreign as you think when you think of
smoothies you might make at home and you
put your blueberries and a little bit of
uh maybe you put a little vegetables
inside there, a little bit of of water
or plant milk or so. That's a form of of
of eating a plant-based meal that's
there, a bowl and berries on when you
think of a of a a salad. Now, I didn't
say ranch soup with a few few pieces of
lettuce. I mean actual robust amount of
of leaves and different different things
that have a crunch factor, right?
>> Um but one of the best ways I love to do
it and encourage folks is using the bowl
method.
>> And so if you think of any of your types
of restaurants to say, what kind of rice
do you want? What type of grain? Okay,
what type of skip over the meat and say,
you know, what kind of bean do you want?
What type of lettuce do you want? And go
that route or potato bar or Italian bar.
that becomes so easy and it gives
especially for kids because what it does
it empowers them that they're getting to
make a choice as it relates to it having
soups, smoothies and salads. So that's
an aspect in terms of adopting it. In
terms of learning more about it, there
are numerous resources that you can look
at. I would probably say the most
exhaustive a lot of the providers, the
physicians and educators out there, we
all have our different style. Um, but
one I would say and I still support him.
I ever I recommend all the time is
Michael Greor on nutritionfacts.org.
That's an easy site. Now, I'm gonna give
it to you a little bit more kind of I'm
not going to tell you you have to eat
this, but I'mma give you the reasons why
you want to eat it. And so, you can sign
up for my newsletter on drbatis.com.
Dr. um Gregor has been at this for about
15 plus years. he's built up a huge
catalog
>> whether or not you're talking about
mental health, if you're talking about
heart disease, you're talking about
rheumatologic disease, if you're saying,
well, are eggs good or bad? Or, hey, can
I have this? And he just is giving you
the science on what it says. And that
can be very helpful um as you're on this
journey. And I think if you take a
mindset
>> and don't focus so much on what you
can't have,
>> right,
>> but you flip it on what can you have,
just focus on what you can have. I'll
never forget this young lady who I
encountered. And so she was saying to
me, "Well, do that. What should I eat?"
I said, "Okay, I want you to start every
meal with a large salad. I want you to
do this, this, this, and this." And she
I'm be I'm going to be too full to eat
anything else. I just smiled at her.
That's the point.
>> I just smiled at her. You know, that's
the point.
>> There's another question, but before we
go there, I want you to be able to pro
promote your conference as well. And so,
if we could put that in the link, can
you talk about an upcoming conference
that you have?
>> Yeah. And so I mean it's basically what
they call like IRL I'm learning about in
real life, you know. So we're bringing
this
right here
>> in real life. And so one is is
understanding the power that you have at
your fingertips and the things that you
do in your daily basis in terms of the
food and offsetting disease. And we talk
about that on day one and we go through
that with experts around the country. On
day two, we're really looking at how to
apply in our communities, right? because
no man's an island and we need to be
able to help our neighbor out. There's a
great analogy or story from like the
turn of the 20th century that there that
fire uh stations used to be privatized.
>> And so they quickly learned that guess
what? If my neighbor's house is burning
and they don't have they don't have a
fireman coming to help them, that's
going to spread to me. And so we see
that perhaps in our neighborhoods and
the foods that have become available at
the schools our kids are at and the
foods that they're eating. And so we
want to enrich our our communities. We
want to empower people to understand
that guess what? We're not telling you
you can't. We're telling you you can.
You have a right to live healthfully.
And that's what the health conference is
about. It's trying to establish a
platform to go out into communities that
are at risk and really helping them to
understand that guess what, your health,
yes, you you need to have insurance.
Yes, you need to have take your
medications. But there's a lot more that
you can do on your own that can empower
your health and that's what the help
conference is about.
>> That's excellent. That's awesome. So if
you want to know more about uh the help
conference, it the link is in the chat.
So please go there and learn more about
that. Um there's a question here and if
you well let's see what you know about
it but I don't know but it's the
question is from Britney. She's saying,
"What's the best place to start if
wanting to learn about the red light
therapy?"
>> Oh, that's great. That's a great
question. Um, so there are some small
pieces of information there. I'm not
aware of a large aggregate. The problem
when it comes to red light, so I just
actually looked this up for an upcoming
episode I'm I'm creating about the
infrared sauna, the red light. And so
the red light is going to give you that
warmth that's there and what it does in
terms of your system. and so forth.
There's the largest studies are probably
outside the US when we're looking in the
finish and and so forth. They they've
done a fair amount of research as it
relates to it. There's not a large
aggregate. You can start to be honest
with you. I would typically Google red
light and research, right? That's the
first start that's there. I don't know
of a great book and that's a fault on my
own. So when I've done it, I've gone
inside of the medical ledge. I've gone
into PubMed, some other things when I
pulled the data. So an easy way without
telling you to go to PubMed, which is a
kind of a scientist physician type of
portal that's there is I would Google
red light and and clinical research or
outcomes. Those are simple search terms.
There's Google Scholar which may give
you some of the articles and say is this
good? Is it bad? Now if you're looking
for more practical terms, then it's more
of okay, how do I apply it? And you want
to once again I would put that inside of
a goo Google Scholar because you want as
close to scientific approach that's
validated as much as possible. So for
instance when I was looking and
reviewing my experience in red light I
saw that 30 to 45 minutes is about the
length of time I happen to do 45 minutes
in that instance but I actually saw that
well I've only been doing about once a
month but actually you probably get the
greatest benefit a couple times a week.
Well, I I don't have the bandwidth to
kind of do it that amount of time, but
you're looking at, okay, what exactly
are the benefits going to be? Well, in
my case, I saw that it relaxes the
endothelium. It lowers the blood
pressure. Um, that it helps stimulate
the immune system too as well by that
warmth and through a mechanism of action
that's too complicated to get into right
now. Um, but you start to kind of learn
about these things and you realize,
okay, there is science and so not
everything that counts can be counted
and not everything that can be counted
counts and we understand that. So we
want to really make sure that we're
looking at finding out first does it
cause harm and we balance out can this
be beneficial without number one cost
number two adverse effects on me those
are the those are and is there any level
of validation that's my approach towards
anything whether or not it's from your
doctor or if it's inside the community.
>> Yes. No thank you for that for that
answer. I'm sure that you know gave them
them some direction for red light
therapy. I want to put the book back up
where you can get it. Selfish from Dr.
Batis. So please let's put that in the
link and we have time for one or two
more questions. And so if you can get
that in want to so say welcome. Somebody
is saying greetings u from Pakistan. So
we want to say back to you. Greetings.
Thank you for being here um on our
program this evening.
>> But yes question. Oh, go ahead, Dr.
White.
>> Yeah. So, I got a quick question for
you. I'm sure you probably haven't heard
of Kachava. Have you heard of Kachava?
>> Uh, yes, I have.
>> Bro, man, what do you think of Kachava,
man? I live by it.
So,
>> my friend, I should say my friend.
>> Yeah. No, Katava, when I read I've read
through the ingredients and so forth. I
think the one thing when it comes to all
of the protein supplements um is that we
have to one is we probably consume more
protein than we need to is number one is
what I would say across the board. Um I
think though when you're on the go as
you're a busy practitioner and you may
not have time to sit down and have a
full meal having that access of
something on the go and you want the
cleanest ingredients as as much as
possible. So once again, first thing, is
it trusted? Is there any type of
validation with it? Are any of the
ingredients harmful?
Then I'm looking at what is reported
with it. So one of the things I'm
looking at is I'm looking at what
percent of the recommended daily
allowance is it? Now, if it comes in at
2% 1%, well, how much is it really
adding? Now, that's not Kachava State. I
know that they theirs is pretty is
pretty high there. and they have a an an
assortment of different um uh quote
unquote superfoods or or thoughts,
things of that nature. Um so it it's
that's my approach when it comes to
protein. So do I have protein
supplements? I do. Do I take them on a
regular basis? I don't. But I know just
being fully transparent with the
audience. I believe in being transparent
when I'm in the Kath lab and I'm busy
doing cases and I'm running around and I
don't have time to really stop like that
having something. So, number one, I have
some carbohydrate nutrients, but I don't
have time to chew. I already told you
it's the powers in chewing. Then that's
an easy go-to for me to make sure I get
it. But you want balance. I And so, I
say that that's important. So, there is
there are studies that tell us it
improves your satiety so you're not so
hungry and famished. But I want the only
reason why I'm giving cautious caution,
Dr. White, is because we live in a
proteinaholic state. We're so focused on
protein. And so I don't want someone to
hear kacaba as a protein supplement and
that I got to get a protein supplement,
right? And that they're taking like, you
know, two grams per kilogram or three
grams as if they're playing in the NFL
or basketball or anything else like
that. So that's only caution. But I
think everything I've read about kachava
specifically, I haven't I' it seems
pretty solid,
>> right? Yeah. I mean, it it's it's I
wouldn't even call it a for me. It's not
even a supplement. It replaces breakfast
for me. Plus, I'll add some fruits, you
know.
>> Um, now I eliminated all that frying
because, you know, you told my wife,
"Throw away all our oil."
>> But now, no more frying. No more my
patakon. But, uh,
but um, but yeah, so I I But thank you.
Thank you for the feedback. Thank you.
>> I know. I love I love it. Now, you
sprinkle some You got your You got your
berries on there. You
>> I toss in my blueberries.
>> Yeah. You get some flax seeds, some
chia, get your omegas on there, and
you're cooking. cooking. Okay,
>> that that sounds very good. Healthy and
good. Since we're asking questions about
what we do, I'm gonna ask you. So, what
I take I drink matcha. I drink matcha
tea
>> for and I don't
>> I typically don't put a sweetener in it.
I mean, people can, but I don't put a
sweetener in it. So, what are your takes
on that?
>> I mean, matcha is a a green tea, and
green tea is so rich in antioxidants, so
powerful. There's so much evidence
supporting the benefits of green tea.
Um, and so I I see it as a plus. Um, in
terms of the the the consumption of of
green tea, period.
>> You worried about caffeine?
>> I think it's a plus, too. It gives me
very clean energy. We have one last
question. What are your thoughts on
fasting for days? 48.
>> Are you asking 48 days, 72 days? Oh,
hours. Sorry. 48 hours, 72 hours, 100
hours. Okay, good. I'm glad it's hours
and
>> so I think fasting. Yeah, that fasting
is ext that's that's an ancient art that
has been validated in studies that we
know that it's beneficial, right? And so
the length of time that you fast may
require you to have some physician
supervision. The type of fasting that
you do, there are many forms of it. So
whether or not we talk about um uh uh
intermittent fasting or timerestricted
feeding, which most people are
referencing, that's where you will only
eat for a period of time of six hours or
eight hours. Well, that's natural,
right? So you should stop eating at a
certain period of time. And what's so
powerful about it is that studies have
shown you can eat the same identical
thing
>> in the morning versus the evening. Your
body processes it completely different.
>> Okay? And your metabolism will be
shifted in terms of your blood glucose,
the cholesterol absorption, everything
of that sort. And so having the bulk of
your meal early morning makes the most
sense. Um there the heavier meals and so
forth, carbohydrate rich meals. Now,
there was a study that brought up a lot
of consternation about a year, a year
year and a half ago, I forget exactly
that was referencing that, hey, maybe
there were worse cardiovascular outcomes
from people who fasted. What they didn't
characterize were the was the quality of
food. Now, you can't fast and have
burgers and fries and and and steak and
and pizza and think that you're going to
have an improved health outcome because
you fasted during that period of time.
So, the the quality of food still
matters, but the time restriction
restriction has been shown. Now, Walter
Longo has done a phenomenal job of doing
uh USC has done tremendous research
where what he's done is he's he's gotten
the benefits of fasting over a five a
fiveday period of time with a restricted
caloric intake.
>> So, you're still eating and you're
drinking teas during this period of
time. And he's shown an improved immune
function, a decrease as far as an
inflammation. He's shown like all the
benefits in terms of diabetes. And so a
cycle of five days at the beginning of
every month. I believe it's somewhere
around um uh 900 calories into like 600
for about three or four days. I forget
the exact amount. And he has a specific
regimen. And so he balances it out. It's
through a site called Prolong. But there
are, you know, one can mimic that sort
of pattern of what he does in your own
life and the foods depending upon how
aggressive you are.
>> Yes. Um just I just want to say on top
of that um just my experience with
fasting. I've um done this throughout
the years and stopped but I'm doing it
again currently now but and I got this
from a doctor and so you have to get it
from your doctor. Don't do what I do but
do it you know what's safe for you. But
I do do 36-hour fast once a week and I
do that for inflammation and I can say
that it does help to lower I have felt
in my for me it has helped with my
inflammation
>> um issue because of my autoimmune
disease but and it's
>> it's not as hard as people think when I
say 36 hours I'm like I'm sleeping for
probably 16 of those 36 hours you know
it's not like you're you know you're
asleep so it's not as hard but
>> um and then when you wake up the next
morning I don't I feel like I'm not that
I'm not hungry at all. I don't have that
hunger craving when you wake up the next
morning. It's very it's just very
interesting feeling. But
>> yeah,
>> so truth be told, I did a 21day fast
years ago now. Time slips by and I'll be
honest, it was a struggle the first
couple of days and then I had this
sense.
>> It wasn't completely no water, no
anything. It was a it was a just a green
juice fast. Um, I had this sense where
everything
came quickly to me.
>> Wow.
>> Like I just felt like I was
>> I felt like I just my mind opened up in
that moment. And so literally and the
downside was it almost gave me a sense
of like you inferior mortals,
you know what's wrong with you? Not only
that, but my senses exploded. my sense
of smell, my hearing, everything just
exploded. Um, and it was amazing. And
I've struggled to get back to doing that
again. And I make all sorts of excuses.
Number one, it's a lengthy period of
time because of work or this, that, and
the other. But I have restricted and
gone essentially um with without any
processed foods. And I have very minimal
processed foods anyway, but I've gone
completely processed foods. has given me
a similar type of of feeling. So I think
the one thing that we're that it's
telling us is science, personal
experience. These are anecdotal
experiences from Dante and myself and
not scientific research, but there is a
plethora of scientific research which
validates really what I described, what
she's described, the process that
happens in the body. And so it's
something to kind of consider looking
at. There's there are sites that do it
under medical supervision. True North in
Northern California. There are several
other sites that do it um as well. They
found they've had phenomenal outcomes
with hypertension with some cancers that
they've reported inside of literature.
Um and so there there is something to
it. Now if you go and you talk to your
doctor about this, if you talked to me
about 18 years ago, I would have just
shook my head at you and said, "What are
you talking about? Don't listen to those
crazy people over there."
And it's not I'm not saying to abandon
anything traditional, but what I'm
saying is that there is something to the
body reset. And there is growing science
as we're reporting more and more about
the power of a lot of these modalities.
>> Well, well, when you're fasting, one of
the things you're doing is you're not
feeding precancerous cells.
>> Absolutely. Th this is why it's so
powerful to eat a little less than what
what would fill you is because you know
you you don't want all of your cells fed
in a sense but no wonderful I find my
energy goes way up because um my body is
not having to digest food.
>> I have a lot of energy by the end of the
day which is great. We have to take this
last question. We have to take it
because it is my sister in love Veronica
Myers. She has
>> and so she is asking does matcha have as
much caffeine as coffee. I just want to
say I don't know the answer to that. I'm
just assuming maybe not as much as
coffee because I could never drink
coffee. It gave me the jitters but I can
drink matcha. So but maybe
>> so I don't I don't know the actual
milligram amount that's there and I
think it but there will be a lot of
factors that will come into play. So my
initial gut response and it's without me
recalling specific numbers is that it's
it's less than coffee but realize with
coffee you're going to have espresso
you're going to have different brews and
types a blonde different ones that are
there that will have different levels of
caffeine and so we know that there is a
a max amount of for caffeine that will
cause harm. So, here's the thing.
Studies so far, for the most part, and I
don't want to speak out both sides of my
mouth, have not really validated the
harmful component of caffeine from
coffee beans or from green tea.
>> Well, they've noted the harmful
components are what we add to it, the
sugar, the cream, and so forth in in the
amounts.
>> Now, on a practical level, that's not
validated by research. I always like to
separate this. I have not found research
to validate this. My concern for
individuals is just what you mentioned,
Tante, is about the jitters, about the
heart palpitations, the skip beats. I
I'm concerned that what happens when you
have caffeine is that you you pee,
right? You urinate, you're losing free
water, which may lead to dehydration to
some degree, electrolyte instability,
propagate arrhythmias um for
individuals, but that has not been
validated consistently in research
trials um for me to say it. I also don't
like the thing that happens less so with
uh those who consume matcha and green
tea. I haven't seen it documented.
Doesn't say it doesn't exist. I haven't
come across that data.
>> Is the withdrawal effect. Is it when I
don't like from like ca uh coffee and
caffeine and so forth. Um it's a
withdrawal that if you don't have it,
you have a blaring headache. You get
grumpy and irritable. I have not seen
that play out from what I've I've found
from matcha and green tea in the same
way I have from c uh coffee and then
obviously all these energy drinks just
as a side note this is harmful to your
body science has told me this completely
um and it will wind you up with not me
I'm a plumber of the heart but you're
going to see one of my colleagues who
are electricians of the heart is what
will end up happening
>> yes
>> profound
>> well this This time has flown by. Um,
Dr. Patise, thank you uh for for
stopping by and spending this time with
us. We are very thankful. I know our
audience is thankful. Want to put up one
more time the book Selfish where you can
get it on. We're going to put that link
up so you can get that on Amazon and
also the link for the help conference so
you can get more information about that
as well. So, we want you guys to check
all of that out. It's always fun to do
the program with you uh Dr. White and
Dr. Batist. Thank you again to our
viewing audience. We will see you in two
weeks. Uh we're going to take another
break. We'll see you in two weeks and we
will be right back here with you for
Mental Health Monday. Have a good
evening.
>> Thank you again, Dr. Batist.
>> All right. Thank you guys.